Shavua Tov שבוע טוב, Shavua Tov, today's daf דף daf is Chaf
Vav כ"ו, Chaf Vav, we pick up with the Mishnah משנה Mishnah
of Chaf He Amud Bet כ"ה עמוד ב' Chaf He Amud Bet
and we continue with the general theme of course of keeping things
distance from your neighbor, but actually in today's daf דף, daf, which
is a little leftover from yesterday's daf דף, daf, we get to
some of the essential issues about sort of the intersection of Bava
Batra בבא בתרא Bava Batra and Bava Kamma בבא קמא, Bava Kamma,
like distancing from your neighbor and how does that relate to questions
about liability for damage and you know when you actually are considered
to be a sort of Mazik מזיק Mazik or the Arba Avot
Nezikin ארבעה אבות נזיקין. Arba Avot Nezikin. So let's take a look
at the Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. Marchikin et ha'ilan min habor מרחיקין את
האילן מן הבור, marchikin et ha'ilan min habor, esrim vechamesh amah עשרים
וחמש אמה, esrim vechamesh amah, we've seen that quoted a lot. You
have to keep the tree away from the cistern 25 amot אמות
amot because the roots will spread, uv'charuv uv'shikmah chamishim amah ובחרוב ובשקמה
חמשים אמה uv'charuv uv'shikmah chamishim amah and with a carob and a
sycamore tree 50 amah אמה amah because those roots will spread more.
So we saw that earlier about the distance from
the city but that had more to do with the sort of
zoning and the appearance of the town, here it's actually even outside
of the town wherever it is in your own field but it's
about not causing indirect damage to your neighbor.
Bein milmalah bein min hatsad בין מלמעלה בין מן הצד, bein milmalah
bein min hatsad, whether the, whether it is on a like, you
know the whatever whether your tree is here and the cistern is
here, that's milmalah מלמעלה milmalah or whether you know they're like sort
of at level ground. Okay, well, at level. Okay, now the question
lamalah למעלה lamalah is what is lamalah למעלה? lamalah? Is the tree
lamalah למעלה lamalah or is the bor בור bor lamalah למעלה? lamalah?
We'll see that in the Gemara גמרא. Gemara. Im habor kadam kotzetz
venoten damim אם הבור קדם קוצץ ונותן דמים, im habor kadam kotzetz
venoten damim, if the cistern was there first, so the person who
built the tree was in violation, then he has to cut it
down and who's making that noise? Is that me? No. Okay. Is
in violation then he has to cut it down but you have
to reimburse him. Now why do you have to reimburse him if
he's in violation? So first of all I want to remind you
that this is, this is less strict than the previous Mishnah משנה
Mishnah about when somebody was sort of doing something inappropriate vis-a-vis the
town. If you made your tree too close to the town they
don't have to pay you for it, the town has more rights
than your neighbor. Okay fine, but nevertheless if he's in violation why
do you have to pay for it? So part of the reason
might be because it takes a long time even though he planted
it in violation, you know the damage occurs only after like many
maybe you know probably years. I know. But anyway but that's a
certain type, it's interesting to see how they made these types of
balances you know because right you could say why should I pay
him for it right? You know he's in violation, it's mine, so
but nevertheless so it is, I do find that a strange halacha
הלכה halacha but partly it has to do with the fact like
I said that it's not an immediate
threat, that's I think
a point that
Tosafot תוספות Tosafot make. Okay, im ilan kadam
lo yikotz
אם אילן קדם לא יקוץ, im ilan kadam lo yikotz, but if
the tree is first then of course he has no need to,
you can't demand that he cuts it down. Safek zeh kadam vesafek
zeh kadam lo yikotz ספק זה קדם וספק זה קדם לא יקוץ
safek zeh kadam vesafek zeh kadam lo yikotz and if you don't
know so it's a type of hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah המוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah, you can't prove that you have
a right to cut down my tree so you can't cut it
down. Rabbi Yossi omer af al pi shehabor kodem la'ilan lo yikotz
רבי יוסי אומר אף על פי שהבור קודם לאילן לא יקוץ, Rabbi
Yossi omer af al pi shehabor kodem la'ilan lo yikotz, even if
the pit comes first, the cistern, you cannot cut down the tree,
shezeh chofair betoch shelo vezeh note'ah betoch shelo שזה חופר בתוך שלו
וזה נוטע בתוך שלו, shezeh chofair betoch shelo vezeh note'ah betoch shelo,
you could do whatever you want in your own property as the
Gemara גמרא Gemara frames it in another place al hanizak leharichik et
atzmo על הניזק להרחיק את עצמו. al hanizak leharichik et atzmo. So
Rabbi Yossi רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi gives an enormous amount of
latitude you know sort of goes against the whole thrust of this
entire perek פרק perek and the Gemara's גמרא Gemara gonna try to
limit it to some degree but basically says you are totally free
to do what you want in your own property and indirect damage
that occurs to somebody else is not your concern, you are the
master of your domain and if they don't want to be damaged
indirectly by you they have to take whatever necessary precautions.
Yes. How does distance fit into that second part? He doesn't hold
of the distance. He says you can do whatever you want. Then
that goes Rabbi Yossi רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi but the first part
of that second part in other words in the beginning it says
it has to be 25 amah אמה. amah. So if your tree
is like 26 amah אמה amah then he has no right then
everybody agrees tough luck. Tough luck exactly. Okay. Tana תנא: Tana: bein
shehabor lematah ve'ilan lemalah bein shehabor lemalah ve'ilan lematah בין שהבור למטה
ואילן למעלה בין שהבור למעלה ואילן למטה. bein shehabor lematah ve'ilan lemalah
bein shehabor lemalah ve'ilan lematah. It doesn't matter if they're on an
incline whether the tree is up here and the cistern is down
here or the reverse. So now obviously you understand in this case
the roots are going to spread and go into the cistern but
the Gemara's גמרא Gemara gonna say what's the problem in the other
case? Right? In the other case the cistern's up here and the
tree is here what's going to happen? So what it's going to
say is... exactly that's what it's going to say. Yes, which twenty-five
אמות? amos? Oh how, oh that's a good question, oh that's a
good question. Do you measure it like this or do you measure
it like that? Oh, that's a good question. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah,
yeah. I imagine you measure it horizontally because it's about the roots
spreading in the horizontal direction, so I
imagine, but that's a good question. I don't know.
So in this case, this would be your measure of like twenty-five
אמות. amos. I mean, I guess if the tree was planted down
here and the cistern was up here, you would
like measure from the bottom of the cistern. No, but yes, you
do measure from, well, the cistern presumably is perpendicular, okay? And the
tree will, but the roots I think we're assuming the roots are
going to grow horizontal. So, yeah, it's a good question.
What? Roots look for water. Oh, that's an interesting point. So you
mean they might go like this? Right, necessarily, but straight would make
sense. Right, right, like this, you mean. Yeah. Yeah, I assume that
that's correct, I hadn't thought about that, but I assume that's correct.
Okay, very good fact. בין שהבור למטה והאילן למעלה בין שהבור למעלה
והאילן למטה. Bein she-habor lemata ve-hailan lemala bein she-habor lemala ve-hailan lemata.
בשלמא בור למטה והאילן למעלה חזינן דשרשין מזקי לבור. Bishlama bor lemata
ve-hailan lemala chazinan deshrashin mazki lebor.
So if the tree is higher and the cistern is lower, they'll
go down through the ground and they'll hit into the cistern. אלא
בור למעלה והאילן למטה אמאי? Ela bor lemala ve-hailan lemata amai? What's
going to be the problem if the tree is below? אמר רב
חגא בשם רבי יוסי מפני שמחלידין את הקרקע ומלקין קרקעיתו של בור
Amar Rav Chaga beshem Rabi Yosi mipnei she-machlidin et hakarka umalkin karkaito
shel bor
because they sort of,
Mark says the word is מחליד machlid is like חלודה chaluda is
like rust, you know, so that they basically they injure the ground,
they loosen up the ground and ultimately they weaken the foundation of
the בור bor even if they don't go directly into the בור.
bor. Okay. רבי יוסי אומר אף על פי שהבור קודם לאילן לא
יקוץ שזה חופר בתוך שלו וזה נוטע בתוך שלו. Rabi Yosi omer
af al pi she-habor kodem la-ilan lo yakotz she-ze chofer betoch shelo
veze notea betoch shelo. So here's רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi who pretty
much goes against the whole thrust of everything we've been talking about.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל
הלכה כרבי יוסי. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halacha ke-Rabi Yosi.
Bet you weren't expecting that. We learn a whole פרק perek with
all these rules, רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi is this outlier position, he's
like the heretic who doesn't believe in all these requirements, and in
the end we wind up embracing רבי יוסי. Rabi Yosi. אמר רב
אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, now we have to push back a little
bit because that's going to, really? Like you never have to worry
about what you might do to your neighbor? So now we're going
to try to limit it, but only a little bit. And I
have to tell you,
I don't know how people feel about this, do you find this
like, yeah, that's a good idea, like you should be fully entitled
to do what you want in your own property? I find it
a little bit disturbing, at least that somewhere between maybe the two
extremes, but you know, a full embracing of רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi
seems like a little radical. Doesn't אשי Ashi only when we פסק
pasken like רבי יוסי? Rabi Yosi? Well, I don't know if there's
any particular, no, there's not רבי יוסי אגלי. Rabi Yosi aglei. It's
probably easier to defend logically, רבי יוסי's Rabi Yosi's position, but it's
like a reductio ad absurdum and a force policy. Exactly, exactly. So
אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, right, that's the whole point, meaning
like in terms of basic property rights, if I'm not a מזיק
mazik and I'm doing stuff in my own property, right, you know,
you have to almost invent the second פרק perek of בבא בתרא
Bava Basra is really like policy. Like, you know, there's no technical
הלכה halacha from a בבא קמא Bava Kama מזיק mazik perspective, I'm
not directly damaging you, it's all indirect and גרמא grama after many
years and so on. I'm doing it in my own property, right,
I mean Dov is right, what technical objection do you have? But
what the second פרק perek of בבא בתרא Bava Basra is there
is to say no, we as the rabbis are going to create
these rules because that's, you need it to govern the sort of
the interaction of neighbors or else you're going to create all this
smoke pollution and all this type of stuff and people aren't going
to be able to live together. And רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi is
just standing on the technical rights, he's rejecting all of that. Yes.
I heard a שיעור shiur on this from Eliezer Diamond, and he
reads רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi as saying you can't prevent me from
doing it but you can come after me if in fact it
damages it. Oh, so that we're going to get to in the
גמרא. Gemara. There are in narrow cases where you can collect damages
from what I would call a
בבא קמא Bava Kama perspective, but that's a more narrow subset. Okay,
so we'll take a look. That, but that is a good question,
right, meaning depending on how broad or narrowly you define these בבא
קמא Bava Kama categories, it could be that you're right, that a
way to think of רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi is that in many
cases it'll be counterbalanced by my desire not to get sued after
the fact. Right, so that's good thinking. But it's a question how
broad those cases will be, how broad or narrow those cases will
be. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב
אשי כי הוינא בי רב כהנא הוה אמרינן Amar Rav Ashi ki
havina bei Rav Kahana hava amrinan when I was in the house
of רב כהנא Rav Kahana we would say מודי רבי יוסי בגירי
דידיה. modi Rabi Yosi begirei didey. רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi would agree
when it's your own arrows, something that is seen as coming directly
from you, that then you do have to keep a distance. So
the only question is how do you define direct, what's your own
arrows? But a good example might be to think about it is
let's say I am making a barbecue. And all my smoke pollution
go straight into your field and causes you damage to your crops
or causes you breathing problems and so on. So there, it's like
there's something that's very direct about that. I light the fire, the
smoke goes up, it happens like immediately, it's a direct consequence of
an act that I did, a product of an act that I
did. So those types of things there, actually, you can't just say,
oh, I planted the tree, three years later it enters your בור,
bor, that's not my business. That's one thing. But when there's some
sense of coming directly from me, then actually you can, then you
can demand. Wait, Rabbi Duby wanted to say something? The smoke from
the barbecue you're saying is direct or indirect? No, that's much more
direct than the roots of a tree after many years. I mean,
obviously there's real arrows. I go ahead and I throw things into
your yard and they break your things. That's like a straight בבא
קמא Bava Kamma issue. Fire is direct. Right. So I'm saying you
have to figure out, it's all a continuum. But there's obviously something,
I light the fire, smoke comes up, it goes into your yard,
all within a few minutes, so the question is, do you define
by timing, do you define by action? But still in the past
we would say the wind caused it and not the person and
we don't blame the person. Right, so there's questions between whether it's
considered to be liability from a בבא קמא Bava Kamma perspective and
whether it is considered direct enough that I have an obligation to
not do it in my property because of like the laws, what's
called הלכות שכנים, hilchos shcheinim, laws that govern neighbors. So that is
the question, how, what is the category of גירי דיליה? girei deilei?
It might be narrow, it might, anyway, we're going to see a
little in the גמרא. Gemara. Yes, Dov? I'm interested in the role
of time, because it doesn't seem like it should really make a
difference in terms of how direct the cause is. But
on the other hand, I know in, I think it's שבת, Shabbos,
that גרמא grama also depends on time. Right, I mean, to some
extent the question about how quick does something happen is part of
defining it as the degree of גרמא grama or not. Like some
people say, like when we turn on a light, right, it's actually
just totally גרמא, grama, you close a circuit and then and then
it causes electricity to flow through the circuit to heat up the
type of thing, whatever. Now the fact it all happens within a
split second makes it harder to call גרמא, grama, even though from
a practical question of the sequence of events that occurred, it is
גרמא. grama. So there is a question of time. I want to
remind you that one example the גמרא Gemara has about גירי דיליה,
girei deilei, which I think is even much less than the issue
of your smoke, but it is about time, is the גמרא Gemara
said you put a ladder, remember you have this גמרא, Gemara, you
put a ladder in your yard and maybe sometimes right as soon
as you put a ladder, some little weasel is waiting in its
hole or whatever it where weasels wait, and it jumps on the
ladder and jumps to your friend's yard and does damage. So my
God, like that was a weasel, I just put a ladder here,
wasn't even something I produced, but because it happens like immediately, that's
seen as a type of my action. Not necessarily from a בבא
קמא Bava Kamma perspective, but at least from a case that רבי
יוסי Ribbi Yose would concede you can't do activities that directly lead
to damage. I understand רבי יוסי Ribbi Yose a bit more, because
if he didn't disagree with half the אוסף osef we had, like
let's say for instance to you, if I put my חנות chanut
there, you can't say איני יכול לישון מכל הנכנסים ומכל היוצאים. eini
yakhol lishon mikol hanichnasim umikol hayotzim. Oh, well no, that's different, that's
zoning, zoning. That's not the same issue. I would not sort of
say that the rights within a חצר chatzer of preventing people from
doing something is the same הלכות halachos here. That's sort of like
it's a communal space and it's a, because there it's about like
our responsibility to a communal space, it's not just something you're doing.
That's more of a zoning issue. But no, but I still think
the question is how much of the previous משניות mishnayos does רבי
יוסי Ribbi Yose disagree with is an important question the ראשונים Rishonim
ask. Like I can't build and make a רפת בקר refat bakar
underneath your warehouse because of the smells. Is that considered גירי דיליה?
girei deilei? You know, it takes a while till I get the
cows in and till the cows start doing their business or whatever
it is, till the smell starts going up, but there is something
more immediate obviously than the case of the tree and the roots,
right? So how exactly in that big continuum of a tree that
takes five years for its roots to spread and, you know, directly
shooting an arrow into
somebody... I'm just doing archery practice in my yard, right? That's a
real גירי דיליה, girei deilei, right? So you know, there's a huge
continuum, where is the areas that רבי יוסי Ribbi Yose agrees, that's
not so clear. Let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara
says. Okay,
פפי יונאה, Papi Yonah, so that's his name, עני והעשיר הוה, ani
vehe'ashir havah, he was poor and then he became wealthy, why that's
relevant we'll see maybe. בנה אפדנא, bena apadna, and he built a
nice little mansion on his property. הוו הנך עצורי בשיבבותיה. havu hanach
atzorei beshivavuteih. Now there were some of these people that were like
that pressed sesames, they made sesame oil, that were in his neighborhood.
דכי הוו דייקי שומשמי, dechi havu dayki shumshami, when they would be
pressing the
sesames... what? שומשום? shumshum? Oh, it's שומשום, shumshum, oh, okay, like sesame.
All right, fine. Fine. Yeah, I know it's sesame, but for whatever
reason, just shows you. Okay.
I tell you, it's every time I teach, it's evidence of the
גמרא Gemara of like שבשתא כיון דעל על, Shabeshta keivan d'al al,
like you know, I learned in ישיבות, yeshivas, what can I tell
you.
Okay. שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz has a שין? shin? Thank you very much. שטיינזלץ
Steinsaltz has a שין. shin. שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz has a שין. shin. What?
No, but he has the שין shin for שומשום. Shumshim. שומשום. Shumshim.
ארטסקרול Artscroll also...
I know, but I understand, I appreciate that. I'm saying that, but
דוב Dov here just backed me up, he said שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz has
it with a שין, shin, not a שין. sin. ארטסקרול Artscroll has
it with a שין. shin. You see that? Thank you very much.
In ישיבות... yeshivas... What? They all went to ישיבה. yeshiva. I don't
know what to say. Moving on.
Okay. הוי דייקי שומשמי Havi daiki shumshamei or
שומשמי, sumsamei, הוי ניידי אפדני. havinadi apadnei. So they would be banging
the sesame and the mansion would be shaking, right? So talk
about a case of גירי דיליה, girei diley, that's your direct vibrations
from your activities, right? Do it like what in its... yeah, near
enough, near enough, that it's causing the ground to shake and it's
causing this mansion to shake. אתא לקמיה דרב אשי. Ata lekamei d'Rav
Ashi. Came to רב אשי. Rav Ashi. אמר ליה, Amar leh, כי
הוינן בי רב כהנא, ki havan bei Rav Kahana, הוי אמינא מודי
רבי יוסי בגירי דיליה. havyamina mode Rabbi Yosei begirei diley. רב אשי
Rav Ashi said we said before, you know what, even if we
פסקן pasken like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei and in רב כהנא's Rav
Kahana ישיבה yeshiva they would say that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei agrees
with the guy's arrows, this is direct result of his actions, the
ground is trembling, so these guys have to move. Okay, וכמה, vekhama,
now how do you, how much, meaning, how much like shaking of
the mansion is considered to be like a threat to the mansion,
right? I mean what, people mostly say oh you can't walk nearby,
causes a little tremble of the ground. How do you measure how
much? כדי ניידי נחמתא אפומי דחצבא, Kadinadei nakhmata apumei de-khatzra, like a,
like
the cover would move on the top of a pot. So if
you basically had a, like you know, a pot there, like a
pottery pot, whatever, and a cover and you put it on a
wall and the shaking would be enough, you know, to make the
cover like move ajar, that was the word, the cover like move
a little bit off the jar, that would be too much vibrations
and then they would have to move. Now what does it have
to do with him being poor and then becoming wealthy? So if
you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says, רבותא נקט, Ribusa nakat,
תוספות Tosafot on the previous עמוד, amud, שהיה עני ולא איבעי לאסוקי
אדעתייהו שיבנה אפדנא, shehaya ani velo ibai l'asukei adatayhu sheyivneh apadna, that
this was a poor neighborhood, so you know, people didn't have a
reason to expect that anybody would ever wind up building a mansion,
you know, on their property. Now of course I don't know why
the other houses weren't threatened by the tremors, but whatever it was,
okay, maybe the other houses were a little more flexible or something.
So maybe they could say you know what we had no reason
to expect this, יבנה אפדנא, yivneh apadna, אפילו הכי איצטריך להרחיק משום
דהוי גירי דיליה. afili hakhi itzrik leharkhik mishum de-havei girei diley. Okay,
אף על גב דסמך בהיתר אין צריך להרחיק אפילו בגירי דיליה. af
al gav d'samakh beheiter ein tzarikh leharkhik afilu begirei diley. Now
תוספות Tosafot raise an interesting question. Once we say רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosei agrees with גירי דיליה girei diley and we create this category
called your own direct actions or your arrows, you know, something more
direct, what's the implications of that for the other question of if
I was here first, I don't have to move, right? I had
my tree here first, I don't have to move. I had, now
let's say I had my sesame operation here first, okay, maybe it
is גירי דיליה, girei diley, but do I have to move? Is
גירי דיליה girei diley enough of a responsibility that even if I
was here first, I still have to not stop doing it? So
תוספות Tosafot says the general rule is no. Okay, let's look at
תוספות. Tosafot. He says, אף על גב דסמך בהיתר אין צריך להרחיק
אפילו בגירי דיליה, af al gav d'samakh beheiter ein tzarikh leharkhik afilu
begirei diley, if you were there first, even in a case of
your own arrows, you don't have to move. What's his proof? כדתניא,
Kid'tanya, אם היה רפת בקר, im haya refet bakar, so here he
uses this idea of the,
I didn't get it out of nowhere, the idea out of the
barn as a type of a גירי דיליה, girei diley, the smells
that go straight up from my barn into your אוצר otzar are
considered my direct arrows. Now to me that's a lot more indirect
than making vibrations or even making smoke, you know, fire. The cows
go there, after a while they start doing their business and it
creates smells or whatever. So it's interesting, תוספות Tosafot considers that a
case of גירי דיליה, girei diley, and he says מותר, mutar, and
if I was there first I don't have to move. הוא הדין
חמיץ של נחתומים וצבענים ואין חילוק בין דירה לשאר כל הצרכין. Hu
ha-din khamitz shel nakhtomin vetzavanim ve-ein khilluk bein dira lishar kol hatzrakhin.
So anyway, so that's an important principle. This little תוספות Tosafot is
making a couple of assumptions. Number one, the barn is a case
of גירי דיליה. girei diley. Number two is that if you're there
first, you don't have to move, even in a case of גירי
דיליה. girei diley. So why is this case of the sesame operation
different? אמר רבנו תם דהכא היינו טעמא משום דלא קביעה תשמישיהו כל
כך, Amar Rabbeinu Tam de-hakha hainu ta'ama mishum delo kevi'a tashmishai kol
kakh, that they didn't really have an established presence there. You know,
once in a year they would make their sesame oil. And since
it wasn't ongoing, therefore, you know, they didn't have a... it's not
like they were there first with enough sense of an ongoing presence
that they could not be moved. But if you're there first with
an ongoing presence... as in even in a גירי דיליה, Giri dilei,
I in my yard regularly do barbecues, okay? And I'm always having
a barbecue every weekend in the summer and it makes a lot
of smoke and then you decide and then you come in, and
you want to do stuff that the smoke is bothering or a
new family moves in and they're very sensitive to smoke or whatever.
I could say I was here first! I don't care about גירי
דיליה. Giri dilei. גירי דיליה Giri dilei doesn't matter, I was here
first! So תוספות Tosafot says the only reason this is different is
because their operation was not so ongoing. There's a lot of important
חידושים Chiddushim in this
תוספות Tosafot about does it matter if you're there first in a
case of גירי דיליה Giri dilei and what constitutes that? His example
about the barn. There are a couple of questions. Yes.
Your own arrows. That רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose admits. Yeah, what constitutes
your own arrows is obviously the question, yeah Dov? What does the
גמרא Gemara question רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose after fine? Because you'd think
it'd be more a question of effort. Let's say for a seasonal
thing, you got a huge millstone, right? That was there. So it's
a big, right, right, right, as opposed to just why don't you
just move your barbecue a few feet more into your property? Right,
I don't know, I assume that in reality all those factors would
be looked at. I mean, you can see תוספות Tosafot is trying,
the whole problem is the גמרא Gemara drops all of these principles
and has all these cases, and then we have to try to
make sense out of all of them and come up with rules
which are not always so clear. Right. Millstone. If it's a if
you just harvest sesame seeds once a year as opposed to something
that you just pounding your normal flour. Right, exactly. גירי דיליה Giri
dilei or גירי דיליה? Giri dilei?
They have דידיה. Didei. דידיה, Didei, right. דידיה, Didei, yeah. Is it
דיליה Dilei
one of the times? Yeah, it's דיליה, Dilei, it's one of דידיה,
Didei, it's the same, same point. Okay. Okay, now back to the
גמרא, Gemara, top of כ"ו עמוד א'. Chaf vav amud aleph. Wow,
people on top of my dictation here. Okay. דבי
בר מיריון בריה דרבין. Debei Bar Miryon Brei DeRavin. So the house
of Bar Miryon, the son of
Ravin, כי הוי נקשי כיתנא, Ki havei nakshei kitna, when they would
be beating their flax, הוי אזלא ריקשא, Havei azla riksha, the stuff
that would get loosened from the flax would go, ומזקי אינשי, Umaskei
inshi, and it would and it would fly into people's face, it
would cause damage, okay? Now that's a real גירי דיליה, Giri dilei,
right? You're beating it, it's you're putting your energy into it, it's
flying out there. That really is like an arrow, it's like you're
shooting an arrow. You're not intending to do it, but it really
is propelled by your energy. All right. אתו לקמיה דרבינא, Atu lekamei
deRavina, came to Ravina. אמר להו, Amar lehu, כי אמרינן מודה רבי
יוסי בגירי דיליה, Ki amrina modeh Rabbi Yose begiri dilei, when do
I say that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose agrees when it's your arrows?
הני מילי דקא אזלא מכחו, Hani mili deka azla mikocho,
that's when it's going through your energy. הכא זיקא הוא דקאממטילה. Hacha
zika hu dekamamtila.
Here it's the wind, this is like you were saying David. So
you may have loosened the the chaff or whatever it is and
it goes up into the and then but the energy that propels
it is actually the wind. It's not the energy you put into
it. Okay, that is an extreme narrow definition of
גירי דיליה, Giri dilei, right? Anything, so what would it be? I
mean,
if you have the case of the vibrations, that is directly your
energy, but my case of the barbecue, okay, you create the smoke
and then the wind blows the smoke. It's an extreme narrow definition
of גירי דיליה. Giri dilei. So he says, no, they don't have
to move. Okay, so מתקיף לה מר בר רב אשי, Maskif la
Mar bar Rav Ashi, so Mar bar Rav Ashi challenged this. מאי
שנא מזורה ורוח מסייעתו? Mai shna mizoreh veruach mesayato? How is this
different? זורה Zoreh is to winnow, not זורע, Zoreia, זורה Zoreh to
winnow where you basically throw up the wheat and then the wind
blows away the chaff. Okay and now, so how do we where's
that relevant? Because you're חייב Chayav on שבת. Shabbat. One of the
thirty-nine מלאכות Melachot on שבת Shabbat is זורה, Zoreh, winnowing. Now, what?
No, no, I'm just, yeah. So, now you don't do it, you're
not separating the chaff from the wheat, you're just throwing up the
wheat. The wind is doing the act of separation and you're חייב
Chayav on שבת. Shabbat. So what you see is, this is a
principle if you remember from בבא קמא Bava Kamma that the גמרא
Gemara calls כוח אחר מעורב בו. Koach acher me'urav bo. You're making
use of natural forces. So even though you are not physically separating
it, you are employing the presence of the wind. You would not
be winnowing if there were no wind. You're employing the presence of
the wind to do this act for you and therefore it's considered
like your act. So the same way that's true for שבת, Shabbat,
that should be true here. You're using the wind and the wind
is doing it. Now there's an obvious difference. In שבת Shabbat you
want to use the wind and you're דוקא Davka would only do
it when there was wind. And here it's completely incidental. You're not
trying to get the wind to blow this stuff away. So the
גמרא Gemara says what?
Well, right, and you could also say that הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbat
is a completely different category. Right, I mean, talk about, let's say,
cooking. You put something on a fire and three hours later the
thing cooks and you're חייב, Chayav, right? So there's a question about
how do you think about מלאכה Melacha as opposed to how do
you think about like מזיק Mazik or הלכות שכנים. Hilchos shecheinim. So
yes, all of those issues come up in בבא קמא Bava Kamma
and תוספות Tosafot raises them here as well. Let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says אמרו קמיה דמרמר, Amru
kamei deMermer, they said to מרמר, Mermer, אמר להו, Amar lehu, היינו
זורה ורוח מסייעתו. Hainu zoreh veruach mesayato. You know what? You're right,
it is just like that case. And it is גירי דיליה. Giri
dilei. גירי דיליה girei dilei and you do have to keep your
distance. Okay, ולרבינא מאי שנא ule'Ravina mai shna now. According to רבינא
Ravina who basically said, where was רבינא? Ravina?
Oh yeah, רבינא Ravina who basically said it was different than זורה
ורוח מסייעתו. zoreh ve'ruach mesayato. רבינא, Ravina, he didn't explain why, but
רבינא Ravina basically said you're not liable, it's not גירי דיליה, girei
dilei, so מאי שנא מגץ היוצא מתחת הפטיש והזיק דחייב לשלם. mai
shna migetz hayotzei mitachas hapatish vehizik dechayav leshalem. Now, the גמרא Gemara
doesn't push the point of זורה ורוח מסייעתו. zoreh ve'ruach mesayato. תוספות
Tosafos says presumably because it realizes that you can make a distinction
between הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbos and other הלכות. halachos. Okay, one phrase
the גמרא Gemara uses in בבא קמא Bava Kamma is מלאכת מחשבת
אסרה תורה. meleches machsheves asra Torah. Now מלאכת מחשבת meleches machsheves normally
by שבת Shabbos is used to say it's harder to violate שבת.
Shabbos. שבת Shabbos has to be exactly as you're intending. So for
example, if I was trying to pick, you know, this אלף aleph
and accidentally I picked another אלף, aleph, I might be exempt even
though I picked an אלף aleph because of מלאכת מחשבת. meleches machsheves.
It wasn't exactly what I was trying to do. But it could
also be used as a way to lower the threshold, because in
it says it focuses on I achieved the end result and the
exact process does not always matter. For example, the very fact that,
you know, you're חייב chayav whether you cook or bake or fry
or all those types of things. Well, I don't understand, which is
the מלאכה? melacha? Well, the מלאכה melacha is more anything that achieves
this type of an end result, it really doesn't matter what the
process is, right? A lot of the תולדות toldos for שבת Shabbos
are because they achieve a similar end result even though they might
come through a different process. That's an idea of מלאכת מחשבת, meleches
machsheves, an emphasis of you achieved what you wanted to achieve in
the end, we don't have a very narrow definition of the act.
We got thirty-nine מלאכות, melachos, we have all your תולדות, toldos, so
you know, there are many possibilities of the acts that bring about
a type of an end result that you're חייב chayav for. So
therefore even if you're using the wind, right, if we had some
other type of thing which was a very focused definition on an
act like, I don't know, let's say I had to take the
לולב, lulav, shake a לולב, lulav, and I shook it because I
somehow used the wind to help me, you know, hold and shake
the לולב, lulav, if you could imagine something like that. Well, maybe
not, there's one defined act and you gotta do it yourself. You
can't do it with other things. But because שבת Shabbos focuses also
on achieving an end result and allows for many types of acts,
it might also allow for using, you know, the wind to be
part of that because it's not a hyper-focus on the process, it's
also a focus on the end result. So that's what a גמרא
Gemara in בבא קמא Bava Kamma sort of says, and basically that's
why the גמרא Gemara here doesn't push the question of how is
it different than the case of the wind on שבת Shabbos and
winnowing, because שבת Shabbos could be different from נזיקין. nezikin. So the
גמרא Gemara lets the שבת Shabbos comparison, puts it aside, but now
it asks another question from a real case of damages, a real
case of נזיקין. nezikin. ולרבינא ule'Ravina and רבינא Ravina who says that
it's not your arrow, מאי שנא מגץ היוצא מתחת הפטיש? mai shna
migetz hayotzei mitachas hapatish? When you are basically banging with a, you
know, hammer and an anvil and you got sparks flying, a spark
goes and it hits somebody, you're חייב. chayav. So how is that
different? You create a spark and it gets brought by the wind
or whatever, and that's a בבא קמא Bava Kamma type of a
case, that's a נזיקין, nezikin, so there's your arrow. How is this
not your arrow? So the גמרא Gemara says והזיק דחייב לשלם, vehizik
dechayav leshalem, you have to pay.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, התם ניחא ליה דליזל הכא לא
ניחא ליה דליזל. hasam nicha lei deleizal hacha lo nicha lei deleizal.
There, you want the sparks to fly away from you because you
don't want them to hit you, you don't want them to, you
know, start a fire, whatever, certainly not on your property. So basically,
I mean, what you could also say is, and it's interesting, you
could say there also your energy is more, you know, directly, you
know, sort of transferred to the spark, but even if that's not
true, you want to use the wind there. Similar to the case
of the winnowing. You want the sparks to fly away. When you're
beating the flax, you really don't care what happens to the stuff
that comes out, it's incidental. So when you want to do it,
it's your activity and you're חייב chayav to pay and you would
have to distance. I would also think, you want the flax, yeah,
you don't want it to get back mixed up... הכא לא ניחא
ליה... hacha lo nicha lei... I don't know, I don't know. Somehow
that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying, you more want the sparks
to fly away than you care about what happens to the stuff
coming out of the flax. What more interests me here is that
the גמרא Gemara without really stopping to analyze intersected, besides הלכות שבת,
Hilchos Shabbos, which you can easily distinguish, it intersected this with הלכות
בבא קמא, Hilchos Bava Kamma, with חייב לשלם. chayav leshalem. And the
question to ask here, and this is exactly, you know, the point
that Gloria was making before is, is גירי דיליה girei dilei just
a case where you have to distance yourself, or maybe גירי דיליה
girei dilei is a case where you have to pay because, you
know, it's either כוחו, kocho, which is a type of אדם המזיק,
adam hamazik, right, or like if you actually shot an arrow you'd
be חייב chayav for אדם המזיק, adam hamazik, or maybe it's אש,
esh, you know, when you create something and the wind carries it,
well that sounds a lot like אש, esh, there's a גמרא Gemara
in בבא קמא Bava Kamma that deals with this case of the
winnowing to understand why you're liable for fire because you create something
and the wind carries it. So maybe all these cases you have
to pay. Okay, so you know, is it when רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi *Rabbi Yose* says you have to, you have to distance yourself
because of גירי דיליה girei deilei *girei diley*, is that a בבא
בתרא Bava Batra *Bava Batra* concern, or is it only in cases
where you actually would be liable from a בבא קמא Bava Kamma.
*Bava Kamma* perspective? Okay, so take a quick look at תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* זיקא הוא דקמאמטי ליה *zika hu de-ka'mamti ley* where we can't,
I mean this is like the major issue of the intersection of
these two מסכתות *masechtot*, right, because sometimes you have to, obviously there
are cases you distance yourself and you don't have to pay. Could
there be cases where, what Gloria was saying is, you would have
to pay but you don't have to distance yourself? רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi, *Rabbi Yose* would say you want to do your thing there,
go set it, but I'll sue you if there are damages. Or
maybe רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi *Rabbi Yose* is only saying when those
two intersect, only when there's a liability, only then you have to
distance. It's not at all clear how to balance these two issues.
So look, or so look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* זיקא הוא דקמאמטי
ליה *zika hu de-ka'mamti ley*. קשיא לרי ולחייב משום אש מידי דהוה
אבנו סכינו ומשאו *kashya le-Ri u-lechayev mishum eish midei de-hava avno sakino
u-maso*. So first of all, how could the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* say,
oh you know, you're not liable because it's not your כח *koach*?
So what? He says, let it be אש *eish*. And then the
whole big תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* works through this question of why it's
not אש *eish*. I'll tell you the short answer. The short answer
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says is, when you have אש *eish*, you make
the fire, the destructive force you've created. The wind just brings it
to another location. Okay, if you go ahead and you loosen up
some of this chaff, okay, there's nothing destructive about chaff. The destructive
power, the damaging power comes from the wind energy. So that's not
אש *eish*. אש *eish* is you made a destructive force and the
wind brought it elsewhere. But if you just create something and then
the wind turns that thing into a damaging force, right, then you
would actually technically be exempt. Okay, so תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* is trying
to figure it out now. Gloria there, Gloria was saying, maybe it
is אש *eish*. Maybe if it's not גירי דיליה girei d'lei? *girei
diley*, you could be exempt from the obligation to distance, but if
it actually does damage, then you would have to pay. Is it
possible to have that almost paradoxical thing? You don't have to distance
yourself, but you will have to pay. But תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* assumes
that's impossible. If we're saying you don't have to distance yourself, then
clearly you're not going to be liable, and therefore you have to
figure out why this is not אש *eish*. It's first of all
giving me, it's giving me a פשט *pshat* now the last line
of that סוגיא *sugya*, למיכלא דזילזלא *le-meichla de-zilzela*. In other words, I
don't really care, like I care that the wind carries the spark
away from me, because the spark, as you've explained, intrinsically is a
damage producer, but the chaff I mean it could be inconvenient, but
I really don't care one way or the other. It's not going
to do damage. I'll brush myself off. Right, exactly. But the other
thing to pay attention to is that this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems
to define גירי דיליה girei d'lei. *girei diley* extremely narrow, right? It
really has to be like your direct energy is communicated. So when
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* before says like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi. *Rabbi
Yose* would agree you put down a ladder and a weasel jumps
out and uses the ladder to springboard to the guy's field, that's
obviously less your גירי דיליה girei d'lei *girei diley*, less your arrows,
than this case about the flax that flies in somebody's face. So
you know, but obviously we're not למעשה l’ma’aseh, *le-ma'aseh* going to limit
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi? *Rabbi Yose* to such a narrow sliver. So
it becomes an interesting discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim*, right, how
to broadly or narrowly define this גירי דיליה girei d'lei? *girei diley*.
But this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* certainly seems to define it very narrowly.
Okay, yeah, the suggestion of beating the flax causing an injurious material.
Yeah, the beating flax thing causes injury, yeah. Right, so I mean...
But the flax itself is not a source of, you have not
created something that has in it damaging power. So how does it
hurt people then? Oh, the wind, the wind did it, right, exactly.
The wind blew something and that hit somebody, right, okay. Right, okay,
let's go on. Okay.
I mean, if you take a look, look at this תוספות Tosafos
*Tosafot*. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* raises the problem just to show you the
last narrow line of the תוספות Tosafos. *Tosafot* we were drilling with,
middle of that last narrow line, ואם תאמר מאי שנא מנמיה *ve-im
tomar mai shena mi-nemiyah*, how is it different from the weasel, דאפילו
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi מרחיק אף על גב דהיא גופה מטי נפשה
*de-afilu Rabbi Yose marchik af al gav de-hi gufah mati nafshah*? The
weasel brings itself into the next yard, right, that's obviously much less
your action. כדאמר רב Rav אשי והני מילי התם משום דזימנין דבהדי
דנח *ke-d'amar Rav Ashi ve-hanei milei hatam mishum de-zimnin de-bahadei de-nach*. As
soon as you put down the ladder, the weasel jumps. But so
what? It's still not your action. אבל קשיא מאורבין דלעיל *aval kashya
me-orvin de-le'eil*, how about the case about the whole ravens, דאמר רב
de'amar Rav יוסף אסיקו לי קורקור מהכא *de-amar Rav Yosef asiku li
kurkur mehacha*? ויש לומר דגמרא לא סבירא ליה כרבינא *ve-yesh lomar de-Gemara
lo sevira leh ke-Ravina*. First of all, you know, רבינא *Ravina* has
a too narrow definition of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei? *Rabbi Yose*. The
earlier גמרא Gemara *Gemara* interprets רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei, *Rabbi Yose* in
not such a hyper-narrow way, in a broader way, that גירי דיליה
*girei diley* would be a bigger category. דרבינו תם פסק כמר בר
רב אשי קמיה *de-Rabbeinu Tam pasak ke-Mar bar Rav Ashi kameih*. And
that becomes an important הלכה halacha, *halacha*, like if ראשונים *Rishonim* were
really dealing with this למעשה *le-ma'aseh*, you don't want to interpret, and
we פוסק paskens *pasken* רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose, *Rabbi Yose*, you don't
want to פוסק pasken *pasken*. Another גמרא Gemara. interprets רבי יוסי in
not such a hyper-narrow way, in a broader way, that גירי דיליה
would be a bigger category. רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam פוסק pasken like
מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi כעמימר, k’Amimar, and that
becomes an important הלכה, halacha like if ראשונים were really dealing with
this למעשה, you don’t want to interpret, and we פוסק רבי יוסי,
you don’t want to פוסק רבי יוסי super narrow. People are going
to be able to do a lot of stuff that’s going to
be really damaging to other people. Okay, this גמרא Gemara is a
narrow definition of רבי יוסי. Another גמרא Gemara. is not so narrow.
ועוד אמרי דבעלי חיים שאני דחמירי טפי מרוח דכח אחר מעורב בהן.
Ve-od omri de-ba’alei chayim shani de-chamiri tfei mi-ruach de-koach acher me’urav ba-hem.
No, no, no. Animals are worse. Now, and he quotes בבא קמא.
Bava Kamma, Okay, animals are worse if I owned the animal. I'm
liable for animals I own. This weasel is not a weasel that
I own. You know, so again it's an intersecting what? כח אחר
מעורב בהן. koach acher me’urav ba-hen. You know, it's like the whole
גמרא Gemara about the, like about the, you know, the first משנה
mishna in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma about, you know, you know, that
about the about why animals as opposed to a well as opposed
to a as opposed to a fire, but then he starts interesting
bringing in these בבא קמא Bava Kamma concepts. But you don't have
to own the animal. No, I can understand that. In other words,
if I live in an area and I know that there are
these vermin, I have to be- yeah, you're not liable from the
בבא קמא Bava Kamma perspective. The liability he references in בבא קמא
Bava Kamma about owning בעלי חיים ba’alei chayim and that they have
like, you know, שיש בהם רוח חיים she-yesh bahem ruach chayim etc.,
are ones that I either own or am directly responsible for. Okay,
it's a conscious distinction. I under- yeah. Anyway, but again, what you
have here is really the intersection of בבא בתרא and בבא קמא
and like this is the fun, trying to unpack all of these
distinctions. Okay, let's go on to the next משנה. mishna. לא יטע
אדם, Lo yita adam, okay guys, לא יטע אדם אילן סמוך לשדה
חברו אלא אם כן הרחיק ממנו ארבע אמות. Lo yita adam ilan
samuch le-sadeh chaveiro ela im kein hirchik mimenu arba amot.
Don't have, you know, your tree, your tree has to be distant
from a cistern 25 אמות amot because of the roots. It also
should be distant from a, it has also to be distant from
a friend's field. Now, רש"י Rashi says field here can mean like
a wheat field, but תוספות Tosafos says from the גמרא Gemara it
sounds much more clear that we're talking here like more about or
whatever, רש"י Rashi says even like a sort of like a vegetable
garden, but תוספות Tosafos says it sounds much more like we're talking
like about trees or vines or other types of things. Anyway, you
have to keep it away specifically like a growing field, not just
like your front yard kind of. Yeah, yeah, it's a שדה, sadeh,
not a חצר. chatzer. אלא אם כן הרחיק ממנו ארבע אמות. Ela
im kein hirchik mimenu arba amot. Four אמות. amot. Because here, apparently,
you're not, you don't have a cistern that it's going to damage,
and a lot of roots of everything that's grown is growing underneath.
So you're really not concerned about roots, you're here out in the,
you know, in the fields and it's not a concern. So what
is the need of the four אמות? amot? אחד גפנים ואחד כל
אילן. Echad gefanim ve-echad kol ilan. Whether you're dealing with vines or
with other trees, this is the distance that you have to maintain
from one field to the next. Now, the גמרא Gemara will say
that the need of four אמות amot is really because you need
four אמות amot like, you know, maneuvering space in order to plow
between them, in order to access them. So you don't want to
be having to go into your unless you grow flowers and you
know you don't have four אמות. amot. Fine. Anyway, let's just get
to it. So you don't have to go into, in order so
you don't, you're not forced to inadvertently go into your friend's field,
you need to give yourself this buffer zone. היה גדר בינתים. Haya
gader beintayim. Now, if there's a wall, which will prevent you from
inadvertently going into your friend's field, זה סומך לגדר מכאן וזה סומך
לגדר מכאן. zeh someich la-gader mikan ve-zeh someich la-gader mikan. Then you
can go right up to the wall. And again, we're not concerned
about the impact of the roots. Why exactly not? Again, presumably they're
not, they don't really damage one another, each field has various stuff
with their own roots. But we'll see more about this in the
גמרא. Gemara היו שרשים יוצאים לתוך של חברו. Hayu shorashim yotzim le-toch
shel chaveiro.
Now, let's say actually what happened was your roots did go into
your friend's yard and now he wants to plow that yard and
your roots are now, right? So you basically,
right, here's the boundary line. I made my tree here. We've got
a wall or whatever or even our four אמות, amot, doesn't matter,
and now the roots have come down here. And this guy wants
to start planting stuff and he's plowing, and like in Israel every
time they dig to make a house they have, they find all
this, you know, all these ruins and they have to stop everything.
So anyway, here he's plowing and his plow hits into a root
of your tree. So now what's he entitled to do? You might
be, you didn't do anything wrong. You were allowed to do that,
it wasn't directly threatening a cistern or something, but he also has
a right to plow his land. So what does he do? So
it says, היו שרשים יוצאים לתוך של חברו מעמיק שלשה טפחים כדי
שלא יעכב את המחרשה. Hayu shorashim yotzim le-toch shel chaveiro ma’amik shlosha
tefachim k’dei she-lo ye-akeiv et ha-machreisha.
He can go down three טפחים tefachim deep and basically cut away
any roots he finds up to three טפחים tefachim deep, up to
nine inches deep. So you're entitled to put your stuff here, but
you have to be, know that he's entitled to cut away any
roots up to three טפחים, tefachim, you know, below the ground level.
So no question of maybe he's damaging the tree by doing that
or- yes, he might damage the tree. That's a risk you take.
I'm allowed- you're allowed to plant your tree and I'm allowed to
plow. Damage to the plow? What? Damage to the plow? Well, yes,
to avoid damage to the plow, I can go ahead and I
see that there are roots. I'm going to go take my axe
and chop away at those roots up to three טפחים tefachim deep
so that it won't damage my plow. Exactly. So you want to
do this, because you say you're doing it in your own property?
געזונטערהייט. gezunterheit. I'm going to also plow in my property and cut
away- cut away any roots that I found. Every point רבי יוסי?
Yeah, I mean, רבי יוסי is the big one who allows you
to do what you want in your own property. Okay, so right.
Nevertheless, I can still cut his roots. Exactly, because I'm doing it
in my property. כדי שלא יעכב את המחרישה kedei shelo ye'akev et
hamachresha
so it should not interfere with the plow. החופר בור שיח ומערה
hachofer bor shiach u'meara if you were the שיח, siach, no,
שיח. shiach. שיח, shiach, שיח, shiach, שיח, shiach, שיח, shiach,
thank you,
once again שין shin over סין. sin. שיח siach is a shrubbery.
It's a type of a cistern. Okay, בור שיח ומערה bor shiach
u'meara if you were various types of cisterns with a, one רש״י
Rashi says one has a building on top of it, the other
is only inside it, anyway, a ditch, various types of cisterns and
ditches, קוצץ ויורד והעצים שלו. kotzetz ve'yored ve'etzim shelo.
So in that case you're now it's not just שלשה טפחים. shelosha
tefachim. If I'm just going to plow then I'm only allowed to
go down שלשה טפחים. shelosha tefachim. If I'm going to dig down
a big cistern like עשר אמות eser amot or whatever, I can
cut away any roots I find and the wood belongs to him.
Of course the question is who's the him? It sounds like him
is the one doing the digging, but the גמרא's Gemara going to
have a debate who the him is. But the point is you
want to do this, געזונטהייט, gesundheit, you're not directly threatening anything I'm
doing, be my guest. But when I want to do stuff in
my field I'm entitled to cut away any roots that I find.
Okay let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. What? I have
a question. Yeah. If the person who's digging that deep area, he
cuts away the roots right? Isn't he going to be concerned that
the roots are going to grow again and injure his area? Right.
So then he'll cut it away again. You know, I mean what
can I say? You know that's right. Okay. What?
The tree was there first. Exactly. If the cistern was there first
he would have to keep this away עשרים וחמש אמות. esrim ve'chamesh
amot. Right. Okay. תנא ארבע שאמרו כדי עבודת הכרם, Tana arba she'amru
kedei avodat hakerem, the four אמות amot is the normal amount of
space you need to work a כרם kerem like that you know
so you need access to it and presumably it would be the
same if it was other trees as well. אמר שמואל לא שנו
אלא בארץ ישראל אבל בבבל שתי אמות. Amar Shmuel lo shanu ela
be'Eretz Yisrael aval be'Bavel shtei amot.
Apparently they had narrower plows and therefore would only require שתי אמות
shtei amot buffer. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we see it
similarly, לא יטע אדם אילן סמוך לשדה חבירו אלא אם כן הרחיק
ממנו שתי אמות. lo yita adam ilan samuch lisedeh chavero ela im
ken hirchik mimenu shtei amot. So we have a ברייתא, Baraita, שתי
אמות. shtei amot. ותנן ארבע אמות. V'anan tnan arba amot. Our משנה
Mishnah says four אמות. amot. אלא לאו כשמואל, Ela lav k'Shmuel, must
be like שמואל, Shmuel, one is ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and one
is בבל. Bavel. Interesting to think that the ברייתא Baraita is coming
from בבל. Bavel. שמע מינה. Shema mina. דאיכא דרמי ליה מרמסא, Deika
d'rami lei Mirmsa, some start with a problem and this is the
resolution that emerges from the problem. תנן לא יטע אדם אילן סמוך
לשדה חבירו אלא אם כן הרחיק ממנו ארבע אמות Tnan lo yita
adam ilan samuch lisedeh chavero ela im ken hirchik mimenu arba amot
והא תניא שתי אמות? v'ha tanya shtei amot? Don't we say שתי
אמות? shtei amot? אמר שמואל לא קשיא כאן בבבל כאן בארץ ישראל.
Amar Shmuel lo kashya kan be'Bavel kan be'Eretz Yisrael.
Fine. רבה בר רב חנן הוו ליה הנהו דיקלי אמצרא דפרדיסא דרב
יוסף. Rava bar Rav Chanan havu lei hanu diklei amitzra d'pardesa d'Rav
Yosef. He had palm trees right on the boundary of the פרדס
pardes like the orchard but it's going to, we're going to see
it's going to actually mean the כרם kerem of רב יוסף. Rav
Yosef. הוו אתי ציפורי יתבי בדיקלי, Hava atei tziporei yasvi b'diklei,
so birds would come, they would nest in the or they would
rest in the palm trees, ונחתי בפרדיסא, v'nachtei b'pardesa, then they would
go from here, use it as a perfect launching space to go
into the vineyard and eat from the fruit. Okay, ומפסדי ליה, u'mfsidi
lei, and they would cause damage. So אמר ליה זיל קוץ, amar
lei zil kotz, he said cut down your tree. ואמר ליה והא
ארחיקי לי, v'amar lei v'ha archiki li,
what do you mean? I'm keeping the four אמות amot away. You
can't tell me I did anything wrong. I kept the appropriate four
אמות amot away. אמר ליה הני מילי לאילנות אבל לגפנים בעינן טפי.
amar lei hani mili l'ilanot aval l'gefanim ba'inan tfei. No, no, that's
only separating trees by four אמות. amot. For a vineyard, for vines,
you need more. והנן תנן אחד גפנים ואחד כל אילן. v'anan tnan
echad gefanim v'echad kol ilan. Doesn't the משנה Mishnah say it doesn't
matter, trees or vines? אמר ליה הני מילי אילן לאילן, amar lei
hani mili ilan l'ilan, if you have trees next to trees, וגפנים
לגפנים, v'gefanim l'gefanim,
and vines next to vines, then four אמות amot apart. אבל אילן
לגפנים, aval ilan l'gefanim, a tree next to a vine, okay, that's
very different because exactly for this issue, the threat of the birds
and the access it gives to the birds, there you need more,
בעינן טפי, ba'inan tfei, you need more. Now of course the question
that you all want to ask is, or I want to ask
is, whatever happened to רבי יוסי? Is this גירי דיליה? Right? So
like you know, we like we seem to have just gone from
one משנה Mishnah to the next and forgotten about רבי יוסי, right?
So I don't know. I mean that gets to תוספות's Tosafos question.
תוספות Tosafos, quoted the גמרא Gemara. before about the ravens where he
said yes, maybe that is גירי דיליה. If you'd start defining גירי
דיליה much broader, you know, so then it's so then okay, then
why isn't everything גירי דיליה? You know, what's the limit? Anyway, he
said look, you know, this is bringing about the birds, it's a
threat, you need more distance. It's not the case of the משנה.
Mishnah. I think I get the feeling he just made that up
on the spot when he was arguing with him.
I don't know, maybe. Okay, anyway, אמר ליה אנא לא קצנה. amar
lei ana lo katzna.
I refuse to, fine, maybe I am liable to cut it down,
I'm not going to be the one to chop it down. Why?
דאמר רב because רב says האי דיקלא דטעין קבא, hai dikla d'tein
kava, if you have a palm tree as long as it can
produce a קב, kav, whatever, a certain quantity of fruit each year,
אסור למקצציה, asur l'mikatzatzei, you can't cut it down because that is
basically you
know. right? But at least, you know, there's an interesting question what
exactly is the technical הלכתי halachic parameters of בל תשחית? bal tashchit?
But certainly in the תורה, Torah, it's about an עץ פרי, etz
pri, a tree that produces fruit, which raises interesting questions. Are you
allowed to cut down a fruit-bearing tree if you can make more
money or it's more advantageous to you to have it cut down,
right? Whatever. So anyway, but here we'll see, because it's interesting. The
גמרא's Gemara not quoting any פסוקים, psukim, it's not quoting any הלכות,
halachot, it almost is going to be making like a מוסר mussar
point. Okay? He says you're not allowed to cut down that type
of a tree. Why? דאמר רב חנינא, de'amar Rav Chanina, לא שכיב
שכחת ברי, lo shachiv Shichat beri, my son שכחת Shichat interesting name
for a child anyway he died at a young age, and he
only died אלא דקץ תאינתא בלא זימניה, ella de'katz te'enata belo zimneih,
because he cut down a fig tree before its time. Obviously it's
very, you know,
the metaphor, whatever, symbolic, right? He cut down a tree when it
wasn't yet the time to cut down the tree, and he was
cut down in the, you know, in the youth of his life.
Okay? So I'm not gonna be the one to cut it down.
I don't want to get that to happen to me. Like, maybe
הלכתי, halachic, it seems like הלכתי halachic it's not forbidden, because he's
gonna say, "You cut it down." So maybe technically it's not בל
תשחית. bal tashchit. It's causing damage, we have a right to, but
symbolically, religiously, it's terrible in terms of that, and I don't want
to be the one to do it. Okay. What does ברי beri
mean? "My son." My son, yeah. רש"י Rashi says the whole thing
is his name, like אף ברי? af beri? No, no, no. I
don't think so. No, he says כך שמו שכחת kach shemo Shichat
was his name. Okay. Anyway, אלא דקץ תאינתא בלא זימניה. ella de'katz
te'enata belo zimneih.
מר, Mar,
you, אי ניחא ליה, ei nicha lei, if you want to cut
it down, ליקוץ, likotz, be my guest. Okay? So maybe so there's
a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot issue, right, or הלכות שכנים hilchos scheinim
issue. You might be entitled because I'm damaging, I'm a threat, however
that sits in with רבי יוסי, but I'm not gonna be the
one to cut it down. Symbolically, this is a terrible thing to
do, you know, from a religious-moral perspective. And the גמרא Gemara. doesn't
say what happened in the end. Maybe he scared him into not
doing anything. Okay. רב פפא, Rav Pappa, now another story, רב פפא
הוה ליה הנהו דיקלי אמיצרא דרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע. Rav Pappa
hava lei hanhu diklei amitzra de'Rav Huna berei de'Rav Yehoshua. רב פפא
Rav Pappa had certain palm trees right onto the border of the
field of רב הונא Rav Huna the son of רב יהושע. Rav
Yehoshua. אזל אשכחיה דהוה חפר וקקייץ שרשיה. azal ashkacheih de'hava chafar ve'kakaitytz
sharshayeih.
Then רב פפא Rav Pappa went and he saw that רב הונא
Rav Huna was digging in his field and cutting away the roots,
just like the משנה mishna says. Okay? Which defines, right, this is
great, like these two cases which are exact cases of the משנה
mishna and they're going to be challenged, even though it seems to
completely be consistent with the משנה. mishna. אמר ליה מאי האי? amar
lei mai hai? What are you doing? אמר ליה, amar lei, תנן,
tnan, what do you mean what am I doing? היו שרשין יוצאין
לתוך של חברו מעמיק שלשה כדי שלא יעכב המחרשה. hayu sharshin yotzin
le'toch shel chaveiro ma'amik shelosha kedei she'lo ya'akev ha'machareshah. That I, you
know, I'm trying to plow my land, your roots are going under
my land, I'm cutting your roots away. אמר ליה, amar lei, הני
מילי שלשה, hani milei shelosha,
that's only if you're going three טפחים tefachim down. מר קחפר טפי,
mar kachafar tefei, you're going deeper. אמר ליה, amar lei, אנא בורות
שיחין ומערות קא חפרנא. ana borot shichin u'me'arot ka'chaferna. I'm digging cisterns
and ditches and whatever, so I'm allowed to go further. דתנן, detnan,
היה חופר בור שיח ומערה קוצץ ויורד והעצים שלו. haya chofer bor
siach u'meara kotzetz ve'yored ve'ha'etzim shelo. And you can even keep the
wood. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa
said, אמרי ליה כולי האי ולא יכלי ליה. amrei lei kulei hai
velo yachli lei. I tried I quoted him all these different sources
to try to get him to stop cutting the roots of my
tree and I wasn't able to win the argument because I mean
he does have the משנה mishna on his side. So I was
really trying to get him to stop but I wasn't able to
win the argument, עד דאמרי ליה, ad de'amrei lei, until I said
to him, הא דאמר רב יהודה, ha de'amar Rav Yehuda, the teaching
of רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. What was the teaching of רב יהודה?
Rav Yehuda? מיצר שהחזיקו בו רבים אסור לקלקלו, meitzar she'hechziku bo rabim
assur lekalkelo,
that if you have a path that the mass, that the, you
know, the public has taken over, then even if they took over
a path on your own property, you can no longer you can't
stop them from using it and you can't damage it. Now what
does that have to do with anything? Right? Here he is, he's
digging in his yard, he's cutting away the roots, "Ah, a path
that the public took over you can't damage." So רש"י Rashi says
it's an argument by analogy. The argument is: the same way when
the public has been going through my yard, that gives them rights
to my yard, so he basically is saying, "My tree has had
its roots going into your yard, that gives me rights to have
my roots in your yard." Roots are walking there. Exactly, roots in
your yard and you can't damage. Of course the question is like,
what type of crazy comparison is that? First of all, it's a
special right that the public has, okay, and that's clear from other
גמרות. Gemarot. This is not a when the public takes over a
place that gives them special rights. Number two is, that goes still
against the משנה. mishna. The משנה mishna says that you are allowed
to cut the roots. What do you mean? So maybe he's saying,
"Well, it's been there for five years and you haven't done anything
for the last five years, is there a passage of time that
now you can't do it anymore?" So it's hard to understand from
רש"י Rashi how a- it in the משנה, Mishna, what the comparison
is, what the parameters would be. תוספות Tosafos gives a radically different
explanation,
right, which is completely redirects the conversation. תוספות says that this area
here, which was רב הונא Rav Huna's field, right this is רב
הונא Rav Huna's field actually, actually, this path here, right along the
way, had been being used by the רבים. rabbim. It was a
path that was cutting through his field that was used by the
רבים. rabbim. And then רב הונא Rav Huna decides, I want to
dig a well in this path. He's allowed to? No, he's not
allowed to. No. So רב פפא Rav Pappa says to him, you
know,
not you're not allowed to cut away my root, you're not allowed
to dig the well in the path. Okay, he's like getting him
from a from a different direction. Okay, I can't stop him from
cutting the root, but I'll like find another reason to stop him.
You're not allowed to dig a well in the path. Okay, so
that's the way תוספות explains it, which is makes it simpler, but
it's less direct. All right, so then the גמרא Gemara continues. Let's
take a look. גמרא Gemara, says לבתר דנפיק אמר lebatar denafik amar
after they left the בי דינא, bei dina, you know, רב הונא
Rav Huna who lost the conversation said, or the the debate said,
אמר אמאי לא אמרי ליה amar amai lo amri leh wait, wait,
wait, I had a retort to him. I could have said כאן
בתוך שש עשרה אמה כאן חוץ לשש עשרה אמה. kan betoch sheish
esrei amah kan chutz lesheish esrei amah. Now, what does sixteen אמות
amos have to do with anything? It's the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim.
So what תוספות says, it works very nicely for תוספות. תוספות says
for שבת, Shabbos, the standard width of a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim
is sixteen אמות. amos. So even if they have used this path,
I can actually, I as the original owner of the path, have
a right to reclaim it as long as I leave them sixteen
אמות. amos. So I actually was within my right to re to
dig that well, because I was still leaving them sixteen אמות amos
width. That's how תוספות reads it. רש"י Rashi reads it in a
way that's going to fit into the later גמרא. Gemara And so
even though רש"י Rashi the idea that you have a חזקה chazakah
is a little strange, רש"י Rashi is going to be very relevant
for the next גמרא. Because רש"י Rashi says when the roots go
under here, we're going to see in the next גמרא that even
though our משנה Mishna sounds like, you know, you can totally dig
and destroy the roots, that the owner of the tree might have
rights to these roots up to sixteen אמות. amos. Okay, and more
than sixteen אמות, amos, you know, then his rights are different vis-a-vis
the roots. So as long as I am digging further away. Now,
the problem is, but the משנה Mishna sounds like you can dig
right over here. Right? So what, how is this sitting into the
משנה? Mishna? So תוספות gets to that and we'll see that in
the upcoming גמרא. Okay, and this is an issue of אלו ואלו
דברי אלוהים חיים. eilu v'eilu divrei Elokim chayim. Yes, yes, like the
case is closed. He's walking out.
Right. And goes, oh, I should have said...
Right.
Right. And so he can't say that now? Right. It's too late.
So תוספות, I just want to tell you that because this is
going to be we're probably we're running out of time now, but
I want to just say that if you actually say רש"י's Rashi's
read, that you are entitled to sixteen אמות amos and the guy
can't dig, how do you explain the משנה? Mishna? So תוספות basically
says this approach would have to explain the משנה Mishna that משנה
Mishna basically would like be talking about, well actually no, you know
what? I'm going to leave it. I'm not going to say because
it's going to get complicated. We'll have to see the גמרא later.
So let's take a look. No, we'll see it in the גמרא,
but it it doesn't make sense to introduce it now. Let's at
least get two minutes into the next גמרא so we can begin
to see it. החופר בור בשדה חבירו וקוצץ שרשים שלו. hachofer bor
besadeh chaveiro vekotzetz shoreshim shelo. You get if you you now you're
digging and you're digging in your own property, you can cut away
the roots and he keeps the roots. Who's the he? בעי מיניה
רב יעקב הדייבא, baei mineih Rav Yaakov Hadaiva, whatever that's his name,
מרב חסדא. meRav Chisda. שרשי אילן של מי? shorshei ilan shel mi?
Who keeps the roots? אמר ליה, amar leh, תניתוה, tanisua, we taught
it. שורשי אילן של הדיוט הבאים בשל הקדש לא נהנין ולא מועלין.
shorshei ilan shel hedyot haba'im beshel hekdesh lo nehenin velo mo'alin.
So basically what you have here is rather than רב פפא Rav
Pappa and רב הונא, Rav Huna, you have a הדיוט hedyot field
and a הקדש hekdesh field. Okay? Now, you have these roots that
are going into the הקדש hekdesh field. And somebody comes down and
I don't know, digs in and cuts out these roots. Are these
roots here הקדש hekdesh or חולין? chullin? They grew from my הדיוט
hedyot field, they grew in your הקדש hekdesh field, are they הקדש
hekdesh or חולין? chullin? And the הלכה halacha, is, you can't get
הנאה hana'ah from them, which is a רבנן Rabbanan הלכה, but if
you did get הנאה, hana'ah, that's לא נהנין, lo nehenin, but if
you did get הנאה, hana'ah, לא מעלי. lo ma'ali. You did not
do מעילה. meilah. Okay? And if you didn't do מעילה, meilah, it
means technically speaking, they're not הקדש. hekdesh. If they were really הקדש,
hekdesh, you would have done you would have done מעילה. meilah. So
it means technically speaking, רבנן Rabbanan because they're growing in הקדש hekdesh
field we have to say you shouldn't, but technically speaking they begin
belong to the הדיוט. hedyot. So this is a proof. My tree,
roots growing in your field, they belong to the owner of the
tree. And that's why there's no מעילה meilah in this case. Okay?
So let's just read that and with this we'll end. Okay? לא
נהנין ולא מועלין. lo nehenin velo mo'alin. אי אמרת בשלמא בתר אילן
אזלינן, ei amart bishlama batar ilan azlinan, if you go by the
tree, משום הכי לא מעלי, mishum hachi lo ma'ali, that's why there's
no מעילה, meilah, because they really belong to the owner of the
tree. אלא אי אמרת, ela ei amart, if you say בתר קרקע
אזלינן, batar karka azlinan, you go by the owner of the field,
they're growing growing in my field, they're my roots. So אמאי לא
מועלין? amai lo moalin? Why is there no מעילה? meila? They're growing
in הקדש's hekdesh field. Okay, so that is it for now. It
looks like they belong to the owner of the tree, but as
we're going to continue tomorrow and we're going to see an argument
in the opposite direction. So to be continued tomorrow. All right. All
right.
The problem is that tomorrow's דף daf or the very bottom of
today's דף, daf, maybe I'm going to draw a picture up here
for שבת Shabbos because it requires diagrams because it's all about, it's
all about geometry and like it's one of those classic גמרות Gemaras
that draw squares and circles and all that. Well, we had that
idea the other day. Right, that's true. I think I'm going to
have to draw a diagram, so it'll be up there before שבת.
Shabbos. What? Every picture? I tried, although my, it was hard for
me to draw in three dimensions.
All right, שבת
שלום Shabbat Shalom everybody.
שבת שלום. Shabbat Shalom.